so there's a lot of things you can do to
alter resting metabolic rate basil
metabolic rate I can't cover them all
but I pulled out eight very specific
ones that I thought you would be most
interested in they have the most
research behind them those the easiest
to integrate and they are the least
kooky is how I'll say it the other final
caveat here is remember just because we
acutely change your resting metabolic
rate that doesn't necessarily mean we're
going to lose body fat in the long term
we'll Circle back to that later
but the first of our eight is what are
called spicy foods people this is in the
lore people talk about it a lot it's out
there a bunch is it really
real yes technically it's true although
if you wanted to consider this to be a
myth I wouldn't push back that hard this
is how the field honestly Works in a lot
of the cases it's officially there but
is it practically relevant I'll just
share with you the data and I'll let you
side now I'll tell you my personal bias
I love spicy foods I put hot sauce or
some sort of spice on basically
everything I eat I love it uh I actually
did I grew up not eating anything spicy
probably even into my mid 20s black
pepper was too spicy for me I my family
just growing up never did anything like
that but I learned to love spicy food
when I started dieting I started cutting
weight and losing weight for
competitions and Combat Sports and
weightlifting and things like that part
of that I'd never done it and I'm
bringing this up now because I realized
man spicy food really helped me in that
caloric Management number one when
things are really spicy I at least
personally tend to not eat as much so
I'm not going to Gorge as much because
I'm dealing with sort of a little bit of
the pain and suffering I'm more likely
to stop a little bit early I don't know
if that's really well documented
scientifically but it's certainly
personally true for me
additionally spices herbs flavors
help you make food not taste as Bland
when you're really controlling stuff so
often times when you're managing
calories you're probably not putting on
uh flavor facts you're you're managing
fat so you don't have the cheeses and
the sauces and so because of that food
can start to taste a little bit Bland
the beauty of
spices and hot sauces is they can be a
caloric and so you can make food taste
different and you can change it up and
have more variety when your total actual
food intake is not that different day by
day so from a practical perspective the
work we've done with people that are
trying to lose weight and me personally
I love spicy foods I used them a ton
here just think about exchanging out hot
sauce or Tabasco for ketchup right easy
win there ketchup has a reasonable
amount of calories you can get tons of
different hot sauces that don't have any
and there you go you've Sav that 50
calories or 100 calories per serving
which adds up a ton so from a practical
perspective I like it if you don't
that's cool too does it do anything
scientifically yes it actually does if
you eat spicy foods and most of the
research here has been done on things
like Chili Peppers ginger red peppers
and even turmeric these will increase
your resting metabolic rates they'll
increase your thermal effective food and
they'll actually oftentimes lower energy
intake like I mentioned earlier we've
seen that routinely there's actually
been research on other spicy foods that
wasn't as promising uh I know that
things people have looked at mustard
horseradish black Peppers those don't
seem to do anything but the other ones I
mentioned a second ago do seem to do
that and they're they're effectively
working by giving you a shot of
adrenaline so more specifically they're
increasing and activating bet beta
adrenergic responses that's the long way
of saying adrenaline or epinephrine and
getting sympathetic Drive you'll see
this like pretty routinely and you don't
have to stretch your imag too far to
think yeah eat something super spicy and
you get a little shot of adrenaline all
right now at the same
time this this is a classic Lane Norton
right he Dr Norton a friend of mine
always talks about people majoring in
the minors and this is a good example of
that so technically does it increase
metabolic rate yes does it do it to a
level that you really
care not really sure what you're
functionally talking about here is
probably three to five calories
so officially it does doesn't matter I
don't know um you have you would have to
eat a enormous amount of red bell
peppers you would have to probably eat
ounces or pounds of Ginger or turmeric
for this to have a real practical output
on you so
Additionally you get sensitized or
desensitized to these things so you may
not have the same response over time I
certainly know if you would have given
me Tabasco 20 years ago
I would have had a much bigger
adrenaline response than I do now and so
since we know that's the mechanism is it
then still leading to additional
increases in my resting metabolic rate I
actually don't think it does I would
assume me personally probably nothing uh
because I'm I'm I'm so used to it by now
so when you balance the like technically
officially I could pull up a a
systematic review or a paper and show
that it increases metabolic rate if
someone doesn't like it or it's not a
preference or they're traveling like
should you really be going out of your
way to strongly encourage spicy foods
for people to boost
metabolism I don't think so right
probably not the biggest win so while I
technically have this on our
list again if you said this is on your
list of things that don't work I
wouldn't push back that much either
moving on then the second on our list is
actually surprising enough water intake
there is more than a small amount of
research on water increasing metabolic
activity if you think about this for a
couple of seconds it makes perfect sense
I actually know one paper specifically
looked at I think like 16 or 17 ounces
of water and found that it increased
resting metabolic rate by 10 to 30% for
about an hour now practically I wouldn't
recommend chugging water all day optim
hydrate but think about what it does if
you're ingesting something at a
temperature that is lower than the
temperature inside your stomach by
putting that in there you'll have to
burn calories to heat that water up in
fact that is actually by the way the
strict definition of a calorie it's the
exact amount of energy it takes to raise
I think it's one gram of water one
degree something like it's pretty close
like the definition of a calorie is how
much energy it takes to increase the
temperature of water so by definition if
your body is working to increase the
temperature of your water then is going
to be burning some calories now there's
also some and I wouldn't call this
extensive but some research on then by
extension of logic colder water might be
of more benefit than room temperature
water it should theoretically take more
energy to heat up okay but probably the
bigger benefit here if there is one at
all is satiety so I know of again
another study off the top of my head
here that in overweight individuals and
that gave them um I think something like
a half liter of water which is a
reasonable amount to drink 30 minutes
before meal and those that group
eventually lost more weight and so what
you're probably looking at here is a lot
of people I I've heard in the vernacular
say things like oh a lot of times when
you think you're hungry you're just
thirsty I don't know if that's
necessarily true or not but having dealt
with a lot of folks who have to lose
weight over time again athletes and
regular people I will say in my personal
coaching experience making sure you're
drinking water will help you reduce
calorie intake the amount of food you
eat in a meal and so forth with really
no consequences to digestibility unless
you're you know going extreme with it so
water is another potential option you
can turn to the effect will be
minimal but you start stacking some
things on top of each other and you need
to drink water anyway so not something I
would say to overdo but just making sure
you're not under hydrated is probably
the biggest win here a similar concept
here but probably more effective is
using a different form of temperature
regulation that is the temperature in
the environment you're in so there have
been several studies that have looked at
lowering the thermostat in your house by
even a few degrees and that can lead to
substantial and significant loss of body
fat over time same exact concept here if
your body has to work a little bit
harder to keep itself at a certain
temperature that is caloric expenditure
you've boosted your metabolism and it
will result in a practical and
meaningful loss of body fat now I
wouldn't necessarily Advocate dropping
the thermostat so much that you're
freezing and your fingers are frozen you
can't type and work but maybe a notch or
two I have friends that have done this a
lot over the years where they bring it
down one degree for three months bring
it down another degree bring it down
another degree and just slowly work
themselves down 3 or 4 degrees where
they used to keep their house at 72° and
now they keep it at 66 or something
reasonable like that if this feels like
majoring in the minors to you fine again
my position here was just to share with
you all the data that we know of let you
know how much it works how well it works
and then you can decide what to deploy
what to disregard or not based on your
situation and circumstances all right so
playing with temperature whether it is
colder water or colder
environment is another option and
probably more effective than the spicy
food thing but still we haven't I
probably haven't sold you a ton on
things that are really going to move the
needle but we're going to change that
here soon fourth on our list is
something I've talked about now and that
is caffeine there is a lot of data on
this I will summarize the entire field
but you can generally expect something
between like a 3 to 11% increase in
resting metabolic rate that's going to
last somewhere between an hour to three
hours this is very very well
documented pretty easy it's a stimulant
it's going to rev up energy it's G to
tell your body to expect energy output
so it's going to get you going nicotine
is next on my list and it has a very
similar effect the magnitude of effect
is a little bit smaller generally more
like five to six% increase and resting
metabolic rate and it's going to last
for the same you know 60 Minutes 120
Minutes something like that now I
personally don't use nicotine we've used
it and some clients they've asked for it
and we've done it with some success
there I personally like to avoid it as
much as I can but those data are there
and and use it how you
will similar and now we're up to number
six on the list is green tea or green
tea extract you'll see this abbreviate a
lot of
GTE has similar effect of caffeine but
in the four to 5% range for about the
same length and
duration as we've mentioned for some of
the stuff prior with water and spicy
foods one thing that has been documented
pretty consist ly with caffeine nicotine
and green tea is they all also affect
satiety so they're appetite suppressant
so is the benefit really in the
elevation and resting metabolic rate I
don't know maybe yes maybe no but if it
helps you just not feel as hungry and
not then
overeat that's probably the real win but
options nonetheless a lot of people are
already consuming these things I don't
think you need to go in there and add
additional stimulus to your life if
you're already on them you don't have to
use these at all but one more time they
are options to use or not at your
discretion number seven on our list is a
combo I had to do it this way if not the
list would have been 50 things or more
and I'm generally going to call these
Thermo Regulators so this is a handful
of herbs and drugs and other stimulant
like factors that are going to have a
similar impact as caffeine and green tea
and so on and so forth but they're
not in those forms just to give you a
couple of examples wonderful scientist
Bill Campbell friend of mine in Florida
has done some work in the past on Guana
uh you can Google that one up there g a
r a an a um combined with other elements
much of the research in this field and
the reason I'm calling them you know
Thermo Regulators is because they're
rarely single ingredient things so
they're multiple herbs combined with
multiple different things and
combinations and Cocktails and so you
don't know what the individual effect is
but nonetheless in these
multi-ingredient Thermo
Regulators in in Bill study in
particular I I think they gave their I
think he did it in young healthy men
probably the college kids that are
running around his lab and they saw
about a 10% increase in resting
metabolic rate for about three hours
post exercise now what I liked about
Bill study in particular of course
because he's such an awesome scientist
is they had a placebo group and they
reported the placebo group what I mean
by that is the placebo group had a 3%
increase in resting metabolic rate so if
you actually kind of cancel that out you
could still see about a 7% bump in RMR
here which I think their data was
something like it took them from about a
group average of 8 or
1,850 calories to 2,000 So 150k Cal bump
from this Guana based multi-ingredient
supplements tons of other Studies have
been done like this one in particular I
know actually several of them have used
things like caffeine plus GTE plus herbl
and stuff like that and if you go back
to the numbers I just gave you on green
tea and caffeine combine them with other
ingredients you'll see about a 10% total
increase again going to last two to
three hours others have been done on
caffeine GTE and niin combined with
actually uh something called Garcinia
Cambogia which was the original primary
ingredient and hydroxy cut you've
probably seen hydroxy cuts and
commercials all over the place I think
there was actually a bunch of problems
with people with getting liver failure
so they took this ingredient out of it
um so it's no longer in there to my
understanding but it was in the original
formulation but nonetheless you throw
all those things together and you might
see a 15% or greater increase in
RMR last one here similar caffeine plus
GTE plus yiman another one showed about
a 15% bump so
you can basically see here kind of no
matter what combination you have of
these stimulants and herbs about the
higher end of the impact is a 15 or so
percent increase for about 2 to three
hours right whether that fits in what
you like and and how you live your life
that's up to you I personally don't use
any of these for fat loss clients it's
not how we approach it but if you want
to there's the data make your choice
next up fish oil now this is a really
interesting one we know of the many
benefits of fish oil but many don't
realize the metabolic ones easy study
here to highlight what's going on 24
females and they did this in I think
they were over 60 656 years old uh if
I'm remembering exactly the age range
there and they gave him three grams per
day of EPA and DHA for a total of 12
weeks now what's cool about this study
is they actually matched it with olive
oil and so calories were equated for one
group get out the olive oil which is
obviously a very healthy food Choice the
other one specifically got fish oil and
so really in smart study design here
because they of course matched calories
they matched fat and they gave them not
really crummy food items or low quality
stuff but two high quality items and so
what that allowed them to do is tease
out the Direct effects of the EPA and
DHA net result here and
remember this is chronic so what
happened not in the the 60 minutes or 90
minutes or 3 hours post taking the fish
oil what happened at
rest 12 weeks later about a 15% increase
in uh 14 actually I think increase in
resting metabolic rate they saw an
increase in energy expenditure during
exercise by about 10% and the fat
oxidation rate both at rest and exercise
were increased about 19 and
27%
respectively what's probably more
impressive than all that though is they
saw a increase in lean mass by about
4% take a second to digest that by
simply taking three grams per day of
fish oil not a high dose at all you saw
a chronic elevation in resting metabolic
rate that at a functional and practical
outcome of a 4% in lean mass compared to
olive oil now what do you think this
would be compared to of a lower quality
fat or Worse food choice in general it
would probably be substantially more so
to me this is incredibly impressive and
it is another reason why taking fish oil
is probably a really smart strategy but
in full honesty here and candidly I
didn't know this I had missed this one I
was pretty aware of basically everything
we talked about so far at this point but
I had absolutely no idea that fish oil
would chronically do this at rest over
time so pretty powerful uh pretty low
hanging fruit and a pretty easy win in
my opinion if you enjoyed this clip you
can watch the full episode by clicking
here